Ashkan Alvand (Ph.D.)

Quantitative researcher

Professional Summary

I am a quantitative researcher with more than seven years' experience in data analysis, statistical modeling, research design and brain imaging analysis. I am independent, confident, self-motivated and responsible, with a drive towards self-development and a continual broadening of knowledge. I am an adaptive team player with a passion for problem solving in complex situations. I am comfortable meeting strict deadlines, working under pressure, and adjusting to rapidly changing conditions. I am also an organized and dependable candidate successful at managing multiple priorities with a positive attitude.

Work Experience

Liggins Institute, the University of Auckland – Research Associate *Auckland, NZ. 02/2023 – 09/2023*

- Worked in a multidisciplinary team on a clinical trial
- Investigated neurodevelopmental changes in neonates using MRI data
- Sorted data into well-organized formats and performed data clerking
- Maintained Unix servers and prepared them for neuroimaging data analyses
- Troubleshot existing data processing scripts and developed new pipelines
- Validated incoming data to check information accuracy and data quality while independently locating and correcting concerns
- Analyzed data and interpreted patterns and trends of MRI data using MATLAB tools, Python packages and shell on Unix machines
- Utilized statistical packages in MATLAB to analyze data and create visualizations
- Co-organized monthly seminars on neuroimaging techniques

The University of Auckland – Doctoral Researcher

Auckland, NZ. 07/2018 - 12/2022

- Completed Ph.D. project investigating functional and structural organization in children diagnosed with auditory processing disorder
- Developed research proposals, identified research objectives, wrote research ethics and created research plans
- Performed in-depth literature review
- Developed state-of-the-art data collection strategies, performed and monitored data quality
- Requested and acquired equipment necessary for projects
- Recruited more than 70 pediatric participants for MRI scan
- Performed data clerking
- Configured Unix machine, Troubleshot and resolved equipment and data processing issues for the study
- Developed new data analysis pipelines using MATLAB, Python and Bash
- Conducted data analyses: Managed and analyzed datasets of over 500 GB, leveraging AFNI, FSL, Bash and MATLAB for insights
- Utilized statistical packages in MATLAB and SPSS to analyze data and interpreted patterns and trends
- Interpreted data analysis results to draw inferences and conclusions

Profiles



https://ashkan-alvand.com/



https://www.linkedin.com/in/ashkan-alvand/



https://profiles.auckland.ac.nz/a-alvand



https://github.com/M31glx

Technical Skills

- Qualitative Research
- Data Analysis
- Data Visualization
- Statistics
- Network theory
- Programing: MATLAB/Python/R/Bash/git
- SPSS
- Machine learning
- Neuroimaging: fMRI/dMRI/sMRI
- Adobe Photoshop/Lightroom/After effects/ Illustrator
- MS Office: Word/Excel/PowerPoint
- OS: Windows/Macintosh/Linux

Interpersonal Skills

- Research
- Data storytelling
- Problem Solving
- Critical Thinking
- Strategic Thinking
- Technical Writing
- Public Speaking
- Teaching
- Human participant recruiting
- Teamwork
- Active listening
- Presentation skill
- Team management

Awards

Eisdell Moore Centre mobility grant, 2k NZD (Nov 2022)

Travel award from Child Mind Institute, 1.2k USD (Sep 2019)

- Create visualizations in MATLAB, Python and Photoshop for presentations and publications
- Wrote detailed reports to present research findings to team members
- Presented findings at an international conferences
- Published 2 peer-reviewed articles in top-tier journals in neuroscience and clinical neuroimaging
- Attended 7 advanced research workshops and courses, honing skills in neuroimaging research
- Collaborated with renowned research labs globally, culminating in 2 joint publications
- Accumulated over 100 citations, reflecting significant impact and recognition in human neuroimaging
- Guided 1 graduate student in their projects, leading to completion of the these

Research Assistant

School of Psychology. 12/2022-02/2023

Research Assistant

Department of Exercise Sciences. 05/2022-09/2022

Graduate Teaching Assistant

School of Psychology. 03/2021- 07/2022

Research Assistant

School of Psychology. 07/2018-12/2021

ICBS Institute, Shahid Beheshti University - Research Associate

Tehran, Iran. 04/2016 - 04/2018

- Managed and Maintained the Unix server
- Performed data analysis, statistical analysis and data visualizations
- Published 1 peer-reviewed article in neuroscience

Publications

- Ashkan Alvand (2023), Graph theory analysis of functional and structural connectome: Links to Auditory Processing Disorder. *Ph.D. Thesis* - University of Auckland.
- Ashkan Alvand, Abin Kuruvilla-Mathew, Reece P. Roberts, Mangor Pedersen, Ian J. Kirk, & Suzanne C. Purdy (2022). Altered structural connectome of children with Auditory Processing Disorder: A diffusion MRI study. *Cerebral Cortex*. https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhad075
- Ashkan Alvand, Abin Kuruvilla-Mathew, Ian J. Kirk, Reece P. Roberts, Mangor Pedersen, & Suzanne C. Purdy (2022). Altered brain network topology in children with Auditory Processing Disorder: a resting-state multi-echo fMRI study. Neuroimage: Clinical. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nicl.2022.103139
- 4. Farnaz Faridi, **Ashkan Alvand**, Reza Khosrowabadi (2022). Brain Structural Correlates of Intelligence in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) Individuals. *Basic & Clinical Neuroscience*.

http://dx.doi.org/10.32598/bcn.2021.2244.1

- Milham, M., Petkov, C. I., Margulies, D. S., Schroeder, ..., Ashkan Alvand, ... & Messinger, A. (2022). Towards Next Generation Primate Neuroscience: A Collaboration-based Strategic Plan for Integrative Neuroimaging. Neuron. https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0896627321007832
- Milham, M., Petkov, C. I., Margulies, D. S., Schroeder, ..., Ashkan Alvand, ... & Messinger, A. (2020). Accelerating the evolution of nonhuman primate neuroimaging. *Neuron*. <u>10.1016/j.neuron.2019.12.023</u>

Faculty of Science full tuition award, 36k NZD (2018-2022)

Ranking 1st among all enrolled students in Master of IT in Azad University (2016)

Education

University of Auckland

2018-2023

Auckland, NZ

Ph.D. in Psychology

Major: Network Neuroscience

Azad University

2014-2016

Garmsar, Iran

Master of Engineering in IT Major: Computer Networks

University of Mazandaran

2010-2014

Babolsar, Iran

Bachelor of Engineering in IT

Oral presentation

OHBM conference (July 2023)

School of Psychology Talk series (June 2021)

BRNZ conference (April 2021)

In-House symposium (Feb 2020)

Hobbies

Bouldering Rock climbing Astrophotography

Languages

English Persian